So the previous video we went through analysis.
This is really a, a two document process for us.
We do the analysis, right, which can be used
as a proposal if that's what you want to do.
Again, this all depends on who you're pitching,
how much you're pitching for,
how many calls you feel like it needs.
For us, we do a discovery call.
Then if they're qualified, then we put together
that analysis deck that we showed you.
Again, that analysis and proposal can be combined into one.
We do the most two separate documents.
We do the analysis, 'cause I like to frame it
as I'm giving you all this value.
You can take this on your own, people pay
for this, et cetera, et cetera.
And then I'll put together the proposal
and scope of work, which is very, very specific
to a couple of things.
The analysis shows them opportunities, issues,
and helps us to formulate for us too
what the scope of work should be.
How many links do we think we need?
How much content do we think we need?
Reviews, profiles, all this different stuff.
The scope of work and proposals very specific.
It's, this is exactly what you're getting,
this is when you're getting it
and this is how much it costs.
So those three things there are really the proposal, right?
The proposed services and the scope of work.
Now, you know, you can easily add text to the back of this
to make this a like a a, an agreement too as well.
We don't sign contracts anymore.
We just, that's just not how, how we do things over here.
I find it just slows things down
and we go month to month anyways,
so we don't slow things down on the signature.
But a lot of you that are doing six months, 12 months,
three month contracts, whatever it is,
you just put the contract language on the back
of this document that I'm gonna give you
and then it's a, it's an agreement as well.
So it's a proposal plus agreement all rolled into one.
And again, you can roll this into the backend
of the analysis as well.
We send them over at the same time
after we do the analysis, I tell them, be on the lookout
for an email and miss sending you the analysis as well
as a scope working proposal.
And I'll usually try and push them
to jump on a follow up call to go
through the proposal as well.
But a lot of people at this point are
just like, yeah, just send me the pricing.
I can make a decision. So it's really up to them
how far you want to take it with how many calls.
Again, you know, we, it's good to have a process,
but you always wanna just be able,
this is part of sales, right?
It's just being a human and just being able to read people
and really understand what it is
that they're looking for and what they need.
So again, the point of the proposal is
to pitch your services.
The analysis to analyze the proposal is to pitch.
This is where we pitch the services.
This is where we price 'em, like I said,
results from the campaign too, right?
So you can also put in
language about expected results completely up to you.
I'm gonna show you what we use here,
but this is a good place to put that as well.
So for example, you know, I don't sign off on it per se,
but when we do Facebook, you know, we talk about
what the expect expected cost per lead is, right?
But it's, it's a bit of a different process than the SEO
process and then also the completed proposal.
So I'm just gonna jump over here to the document
because there's really, there's really
two things that we need to cover.
One is the actual proposal, scope
of work document statement of work document.
And two is pricing. Pricing is rolled into
this part of the process here.
So we're gonna spend some time talking about pricing
as well, how we scope and
How we price things.
I'm gonna open it up for questions at that point too
because there's always a lot of questions about pricing
and there's a number of ways to do it.
I'm gonna, I'm gonna walk you through how we do it.
So this right here is our latest and greatest.
I literally just made a copy of this.
This just went out today for a law firm prospect.
Yeah, please don't copy this, it's yours to make a copy of.
But please modify it.
You know, even if you just throw it into chat.
GPT, this is all written by chat GPT by the way,
it's nothing fancy here.
It's not like we had a copywriter do it,
but let me just walk you through it
on the finer points here.
So again, this goes out
with an email along with the analysis.
We send this in here as well
and it just very details goes through all the items
that are included inside of their scope of work.
And it's broken down with examples and just a lot of detail.
And a lot of times, like I said, it's good to get on a call
and run them through this too, so
that way you can get on the same page
about everything that's included.
We just put this into our proposals like two weeks ago
because just a lot of attorneys are like, Hey,
what about web, like our, our past agencies doing website
management, we don't wanna lose that capability.
And I'm like, what are they doing?
They're like, oh, they're managing the website.
I'm like, yeah, well what, what, what's the scope of work?
They're like, I don't know, like posting
and content updates.
I'm like, oh, okay, so like SEO stuff we're already doing,
so why don't I just put it in here?
As well as kind of like an added benefit.
So again, chat ccbt wrote this for me.
It just basically just says we're gonna manage the,
we're gonna manage the website.
Again, that was a funny joke that comes
to mind from a sitcom where he is like talking about
how like you can just write things off
and he's like, you don't even know what that means.
He's like, yes I do. It means that you write it off.
It's like, write it off to who?
He's like, you just write it off.
And the same thing here, like, I dunno what it means,
but it means what do you want me?
And again, you guys can read through this,
but essentially it's just, you know,
website management maintenance.
It's just a good light item that we
find we were getting asked about.
So we added it in. It doesn't require any additional scope
of work because we're already doing it,
we're doing content management.
You know, if they're like, Hey, can you update
our attorney bio page?
That's like what they have in mind.
They're like, if we have a new attorney come on board,
how do we update the website and
what you could just ask us to, you know?
But now we're putting in here as a line item, as a,
as a good thing to have tracking analytics.
So you know, again, go through this
and make sure that you're covering all this is why I also
don't want you to copy it because like you don't want
to put into writing something that you're, that, that we do
that you're not going to do.
It can come and bite you in the butt pretty hard.
So GA four set up conversions.
We do front end call tracking CallRail
or what converts if they have it.
If they don't have it, then we'll set it up.
Conversion tracking if we're running ads for them, right?
So meta Google as well.
Lead tracking and automatic integration into CRM
tagging leads where they come from.
Close deal tracking, 360 targeting
and then custom dashboard reporting a month in review.
So I like to put in examples as well.
Again, these are our examples
so you don't wanna send
them over, you're not gonna look good.
But just a link to show them a
little bit about what they can expect.
I believe this is just an, I
don't even know if this is working anymore.
This is an agency analytics like snapshot
dashboard that I just put in here.
And again, this is why it's also good to run them
through this stuff on a call.
Okay, this is working just so they can see, you know,
what the reporting dashboard looks like.
I feel like when,
when it's too too much words, it's good to have some
Visuals in here as well. But
you don't wanna be putting like screenshots in here
because then this thing will be like 30 pages long.
You want them to be able to get through this quickly.
But show them examples and these are really good.
Again, if you're walking them through it on call for you
to say this is what our dashboards look like.
If you have any questions, et
cetera, then we get into technical.
SEO just talks about again, some roadblocks
and then some more kind of like detailed scope work things.
Again, chat. GPT wrote this for me, I fed our analysis.
I said I need these bucketed itemized.
Can you write these in the bullet points for me?
Four pages, core red vitals,
multi-language translation optimizations.
We do all that stuff. Again, you wanna make sure you read
through this to make sure that you do it
and make sure it's, it's really tailored
and customized to the client that you're working with.
These are hit or miss man.
I just have some links in here too
of like example deliverables.
I don't even know if these get looked at or not,
but you know, what does a read like, especially
for attorneys, I know they're not looking at, it's just kind
of like, okay, spreadsheets, nice, they're not dumb.
So tech SEO.
Now we get into local S-E-O-D-V-P optimization,
everything that's included in that.
And it doesn't have to be an exhaustive list list, like
to me this is just kind of like a,
a check in the box thing for them.
When I get asked a lot
of questions on calls, like, oh is this included?
Is that included? Just like the website management stuff,
you just wanna make sure it's included here
and obviously make sure that you're doing it too.
But this is also good for you to understand like
what are people asking about
that we should be talking about ahead of time
and making sure that we're telling
them that this is included.
'cause obviously it's important to them. You know,
citations management, review management,
secondary directory optimization.
We'll manage all locations
with a verified GBP website content creation.
So this is where it starts to get case by case basis.
Everything is, this whole thing is templated.
Really the things that we're changing are the word count.
So again, what we're doing here, content matrix outlines,
drafts, content, uploading, formatting, publishing.
If you're not doing that, don't put it in here.
That's very important. Number two, the scope of content.
What types of pages are we going to be working on
as a part of this campaign?
Location pages, practice area pages,
and then blog supporting content.
Probably very similar for a lot of you,
but again, you just wanna make sure that you customize this
to the type of content that you're working on.
And then again, this especially is what you wanna customize.
So we're gonna come back to this in a second in terms of
how much content is needed.
We'll talk about that in a moment when we get into the
pricing section, 'cause that's
where really the pricing stuff comes into play.
But just make a note mentally
that you wanna make sure you're updating this.
And then just content examples,
these are easy, these are good to have.
Practice area, page, blog content, et cetera.
Link acquisition. Now again, this is another one
that you're gonna wanna make sure is highly tailored
to the type of client that you are working with.
So I talk about this in the link building training.
We have link building tiers, tier three, tier two,
and tier one also too, like I have that we we,
we do prospecting, outreach, content writing is needed,
tracking, reporting, all that stuff that's included.
You can just leave that in there. Tier three,
tier two, tier one.
The reason why I have these in here
with examples is very important.
And that's because it clearly says here we will build
and optimize 25 tier three websites
and five tier two websites monthly.
The cost to acquire these links is included in
the proposed monthly retainer.
Again, we're gonna talk about this in a second.
We'll get into pricing, just bear with me.
The Webers team will provide a tier list
of tier one opportunities as we come across 'em.
However, the cost of these
links will be paid to their clients.
It's really important that we have that in here
because that way, you know, like this website for example,
I think this, well, they took it down,
but this is like a $500 placement.
We're not gonna take that out of our
retainer, but they should be on it.
So let's present it to 'em
and if they go for it then we'll do it.
If not, we're doing tier two contextual link sponsor,
post guest posts, et cetera.
And this is mainly, these two are from our database
and we're actually doing more than 25 tier threes.
I like to kind of put a floor in here.
We're gonna, again, we're gonna talk about scoping
and pricing from part of it, but I like to put more
of a floor than a ceiling
because I don't wanna put like,
we're gonna do 500 if we're not gonna do that.
So it's like a minimum of 25.
So when I walk 'em through this, I tell 'em the same thing.
I say, look it, you can expect a minimum of 25,
but you know we're gonna end up doing like 70.
'cause that's what our list is. So then I also threw in this
section here about GEO and completely written by chat.
GPT just goes into, uh, a little bit
of the details about specifically
what's included inside of that.
So that is the scope of work.
So that's what they are getting it.
Now I need to move this down a little bit. Sorry.
Now we need to get into when are they getting it
and how much are they paying for the other two questions.
So when are they getting it is very simple.
We just have this, this layout here over six months.
But Ryan, you don't do monthly contracts. Yeah, absolutely.
But we wanna make sure that they see
that this is not a one month service, right?
So you can lay this out over 12 months.
If you're doing 12 month contracts, that's important.
I find that after month
six you're just doing the same thing.
So it's a little bit stupid to have 12 months on here
and it also just fits better too visually.
But you can see here you also have access
to this spreadsheet that you'll have.
This is, we're gonna start going into this in a little bit
more detail about how
to fill this out in the different ways to fill it out.
So let's just walk through real quick.
This is our standard proposal. We don't change this.
The only thing we change is content creation
in terms of words per month.
And then link acquisition, how many links per month?
So again, analytics website optimizations, local SEO,
and you can see and hear
what we're doing on a monthly basis for that line item.
We used to price per hour
and we used to put like hours in here.
But then I don't like hourly
pricing for a number of reasons.
One, if they check the hours
and you're not tracking them, which you're not,
it can come back to bite you two.
When they see hours, they're gonna expect hours.
If you're not doing it, it can come back to bite you three.
They don't care. You know?
And like it's not a good precedent for you to set
that like you're being managed on an hourly basis.
You're not an employee, you're getting paid for results.
You're not getting paid an hourly wage.
Now you can use hours, you should be using hours to track
how to price things in terms of
how much should I charge for analytics work.
Because you need to know what it costs you to do it.
You're not just pulling numbers outta your,
but you wanna say, okay, for us to deliver on this,
this takes five hours
of a contractor's work per time at 5,000, I want
to make at least 50% markup on what we do.
So I'm gonna charge $500 for analytics, right?
That's how we price, that's how we do our pricing.
And then once you get to a point where we're doing this over
and over again, you don't need to show that.
You don't even need to think about it.
You just look at this and the only,
the only variable cost becomes content
and links, which I'm gonna talk about in a second.
Does that make sense? Same thing with website optimizations.
You know, it's really a one or two month thing.
I could add website management in here,
but it would just be like management.
It wouldn't really say anything local.
SEO, again, you know, we just kind
of have these split out just to show
that there's things going on.
But really mostly this is like a one time thing.
And then we're just doing some
review, outreach and citation building.
But citations are also links.
So let's get into concept creation.
So the first month is strategy.
That's just so they're not expecting, you know, us
to start cranking out words per month.
Even though the first month we do start writing 20,000
words, let's call it, it's about three,
well it's about 2,500 per page, right?
Is what we do on average 2,500 words per page.
So that's about eight pages per month.
This number, the number of words keeps on going up for us
because our content is getting so efficient with AI
that our cost keeps going down.
So we're able to do more and more content per people.
So 20,000, this is for a bigger pitch, right?
If this was gonna be a, like this firm
that we're pitching right here was a like six location
injury firm, right?
So they needed like
how can you determine how many words are needed?
Well, you go back to your analysis
and you say, do they have all the pages necessary?
Do they have all their practice area pages, location pages?
If they have them, do they need
to be rewritten and optimized?
All that should count, figure into your word count.
So what we do inside of our analysis is,
if you recall from the last meeting, we have a, like a kind
of a mini content app analysis says, Hey,
you have six locations,
but for each location you should have
10 practice area pages.
That's 60 pages right there.
Pages, you only have 20 of those 60,
that's 40 pages right there.
40 pages at 2,500 words per pop.
That is a hundred thousand words, right?
So a hundred thousand divided
by 20,000 is five, that's five months.
That's probably too long to get all that content done.
You might want to truncate that and shrink that
and bump it up to 30,000 or 40,000 words.
Now again, you need to be really good using AI
content to get that done.
And this is also why you need to be only working
with a single type of client.
We can, we can do a hundred thousand words a month
because we've got all the templates done,
we've done 'em a million times, we're just feeding it
to AI to rewrite them.
But if we were to somebody come up to us as e-commerce store
and be like, Hey, we need a hundred thousand words
of content, I'll be like, that's
we're, we're not gonna be able to do that.
We don't have the process, we don't have the templates.
It's not what we do. So it's why it's important.
Again, we talk about inside of the content module,
we talk all about AI content and exactly our process.
You can see how we do that. So that's
how we scope content right now, for the most part, again,
we don't necessarily adhere
to the word count when we're delivering the work.
For example, this client is probably gonna end up getting
50,000 words the first couple of months.
This is a floor that I tell them, right?
Because I also don't want to put in here 50,000 words
because then they're gonna expect, right?
And then in month eight after we've hammered out all those
words, they're gonna be like, yeah, like 50,000 words,
that's 15 pages a month.
Why aren't doing 15 pages a month?
So I like to tell 'em, this is the floor, right?
This is the minimum that they need.
Nobody's gonna balk at 20,000 words.
They're gonna be like, oh wow, that's quite a bit, you
Know, know, you also need to understand
what your cost per content
internally is in order to do that.
So we know what our cost per word is.
That's why we price per word. We used to price per page.
But then it was like, okay, blog post is
different than a homepage is different.
So we just do it per word. Our cost per word used
to be 30 cents per word, right?
So 30 cents times 20,000.
It used to cost a thousand dollars
to do this level of content.
That's 'cause we were paying writers.
Now we've got our cost per content down
to like 3 cents per word because of ai, right?
So when we do three times 20,000, we're looking at six
for the, for the content costs, right?
That doesn't necessarily include like all the labor
that goes into it, but you can start to see the how the mar,
I mean the swing on that margin is crazy, right?
Not just the swing on the margin,
but also the swing on the outcome and the results.
If this client really needed 20,000 words a month
beforehand, we would have to be doing like 5,000 words a
month and it would take much longer
to get the content developed.
Now with ai, thank God, we're able
to sprint this out very quickly at a very low cost.
So that's how we scope content, right?
It's very important that you understand what,
how much content is needed, but also just as importantly,
how much does it cost us?
Because what I'll tell clients too, if they ask,
they usually don't ask us like, Hey,
what's the cost per when they see all this,
they don't usually go in item, they never go in itemized.
They're never like, Hey, what's the cost per word?
What's the analytics cost?
Like, they just see the flashy and they're good with it.
They're like, oh, there's a lot of stuff going into it.
I get it right now. Same thing with links first month.
You know, we're not necessarily starting
with link buildings really to save us on cost,
but also how are we scoping how many links are needed?
So this is much more of an internal cost than an
external link amount needed.
What do I mean by that? Well, in the analysis, again, we do
that head-to-head comparison of links
that you have versus the mar versus the the top
competitors in your market.
So let's say this client, for example,
had 50 referring domains.
The top competitor had a thousand, that's a 20 x increase.
Now not all links are created equal, right?
One link, a good link might be worth 10 of their links.
But this is just roughly speaking here,
we don't have the ability to actually do that level analysis
with the time that we're given.
So we're saying, okay, if we can get 10 links per month,
that's 50 links over five months,
it's gonna take us years to close that gap.
It kind of is what it is, right?
Like, because if I'm gonna quote them on the number of links
that they really need, the cost
of this is just gonna skyrocket through the roof
and they're probably not gonna pay for it, you know?
Now that being said, we usually don't come across those
types of pitches where somebody is like, if they're that,
if they're that deficient in links,
then I'm usually pitching them paid ads.
I, I'm always pitching to paid ads.
Like if I get into a situation where it's like, hey,
you have five links, yours is a brand new website
and the competition has been doing this for 10 years.
I'm not pitching the mess EO, like I'm not even getting
to this point because it's just a drop in the bucket, right?
So I'm doing PPC or Facebook ads in those instances.
And that's very easy to tell. It's basically, hey,
you're a new firm, you got a new website,
we should probably focus on pay ads.
Not all the time, but most of the time, right?
If they're adamant about doing
SEO, I'm just very honest about it.
And I tell them, this is why like you need to pay more
because we need to get a lot of links
and those links to us have a have a hard cost.
So you need to understand what your hard,
hard cost is per link.
How do you understand what your hard cost per link is?
Well, every link that you get has a cost.
That's actually an easy thing, right?
So like we have a link manager, we pay 'em a set,
a set salary per month, right?
For every link. Let's say we build a hundred links a month,
we just go and we tally up what would those costs per links.
It usually comes around, I think $200 on average cost per
link plus his, his salary goes into that.
We divide it by, you know, whatever.
And that's how we know what our cost per link is, right?
So a hundred links tally up the cost inside of Excel,
throw his cost inside of it, divide it by a hundred,
and that's when we know what our cost per link is.
Again, it usually comes around 200 bucks.
So we have a hard cost for 200 bucks per link.
That means, again, I need to know how much I can,
if we're eating this, we're eating this
out of the retainer, right?
So like this cost comes outta the retainer,
this cost comes outta the retainer.
We have a set amount that profit that we want
to hit in terms of operating costs
where I'm not gonna just pitch him,
pitch them 40 lengths a month.
That's gonna cost me 40 times 200,
it's gonna cost me eight grand.
Now again, case by case, that might call for it.
Or maybe we'll tell 'em to go hire a PR company
or we need to do tier one links or whatever that looks like.
Point is that, that I'm zeroing it on is
that this usually usually do a max
of like 12 links per month
because for the most part we're getting good links.
And again, our links count more in velocity
and in terms of ranking prowess than the competitors do.
So we don't have to hammer it
with like a hundred links per month
and just the cost gets outta control.
And you have to be mindful when you're selling
of like what is their threshold?
What is their budget? What is the
expectation on their end of pricing?
If you come in here and you really have to pump this up,
this gets up to 20,000.
They're just gonna bach because of the cost per link.
So this is where like the strategy of SEO pricing
and selling is so important
because you need to know what your costs are in order
to really pitch this stuff properly.
Does that make sense? And then GS just all added in here.
So again, this is, this total number here is
for us is based on number of locations that they have,
amount of content that we need to write
and amount of links that we need to build.
And I usually like to try and hit, I usually like to try
and maintain like $7,000 of, of, of profit
after these costs come out of it.
And that's not even profit, right? That's just $7,000
after the expenses come out of it, right?
So we allocate, you know, 20 to 30% of the top line revenue
that we get sprayed out the door for
for those types of types of costs.
It's one of the reasons why SEO is so damn expensive.
Why we have to charge, and I, I make sure to explain this
to prospects too so they understand.
So again, this is our underneath it.
This is just kind of like our agreement wording.
It's very simple, but you can put your agreement wording,
just paste it underneath it.
So you've also got access to the spreadsheet here.
I'll just walk you through this real quick.
If you're building this from the ground up,
what I would suggest is refilling out
this template for yourself.
So you have everything that you do inside of here,
and then this just becomes a literal copy
and paste job into this section here.
So this for us has everything.
This is like the kitchen sink offer, right?
It has everything that we could and would be doing.
So I even have like video stuff in here.
I don't pitch it ever, but it's in here.
Advertising sprints are in here as well, right?
If we're doing like a multi multi-service pitch, PPC
and Facebook, they just, we don't even do a proposal form,
we just kind of send them an email.
It's very easy. And then here's a truncated version.
And then again, here's another option too.
If you wanted to do hourly pricing,
or this might be helpful for you to fill this out
so you know how much it costs.
So instead of sprints,
this could be like your internal costs.
And then these are the same one here.
They're just different sprints.
So this is just important for you to understand
what your costs are so you can really know how
to pitch these things if you don't have your
costs in your buckets.
And a line like your profit margins are always gonna
be all over the place.
You have to get a handle on this stuff.
You absolutely have to get a handle on it
and uh, you know, it might take some time to do that,
especially if you're just getting started.
You're like, how am I, how do I know
how much analytics costs or technical SEO costs?
Well, you have people, it's people time.
You track the cost of the people,
you can also track the cost of the tools that it takes.
You throw those all in and you add them up
and you divide 'em out and then you're able to figure out
what that costs on a per client basis.
So tracking people's hours in the beginning is very
important until you get to a point where
for us it's like, I don't, we don't need to think about it.
You know, like we know exactly what this takes us.
It's about 10 hours for like the tech SEO work.
And it might take more, it might take less,
but like, it doesn't, it doesn't kill us either way.
You know, we're talking about a couple hour swing.
It's really the content and the links
that can really crush you,
especially if you're not using AI content writing
or you don't have a good system down yet
and links, you know, for obvious reasons, links can add up.
Just wanted to, to really nail down the pricing side of this
'cause it's usually a very deep conversation.